ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
THE NORTHERNMOST POINT OF THE CONTINENT
（在大陆极北之境）
I REACHED AUREOLE, THE LAND WHERE SOULS REST,
（我抵达了灵魂长眠之地 那是灵魂安息的所在）
A PLACE WHICH THE PEOPLE OF THIS WORLD CALL HEAVEN
（这个世界的人称那里为天国）
THERE WERE MANY SOULS GATHERED THERE
（在那里聚集了众多灵魂）
AND I TALKED TO MY FORMER COMRADES
（我与昔日战友进行了对话）
THE GREAT MAGE FLAMME
（大魔法使伏拉梅）
Frieren.
芙莉莲
The royal capital is within sight now.
能看到王都了
The party of heroes is making a triumphant return home.
我们勇者一行凯旋而归
I bet they're filled with excitement.
我敢说城里的大家一定很雀跃
Once we get back, I have to look for a job.
回去就得马上找工作了
You're thinking about that already?
你已经在想这些事啦？
It's important.
这很重要
It doesn't end just because we took down the Demon King.
虽然已经打倒了魔王 但人生可不是就此结束了
We have our whole lives ahead of us.
之后要走的路还长得很
-A job, huh? -I want a job where I can drink.
-工作吗？ -有能喝酒的工作就好了
Excuse me, you're a priest.
你不是僧侣吗？
That's true…
说得也是…
Frieren,
芙莉莲
you are probably going to live for so much longer
你之后的人生肯定长到我们
than we can even imagine.
无法想象的地步
Maybe.
说得是呢
Himmel, the hero.
勇者辛美尔
Eisen, the warrior. Heiter, the priest.
战士艾泽 僧侣海塔
Frieren, the mage.
魔法使芙莉莲
You did well in taking down the Demon King.
讨伐魔王一事辛苦各位了
Now, an era of peace will come upon this world.
自此之后 这个世界就能迎来和平
The king is apparently going to erect statues of us in the plaza.
据说国王要在广场竖立我们的雕像
Although, I'm still very skeptical whether they can accurately depict
虽然本人帅气的程度之高 让我相当怀疑他们是否
how handsome I am.
能够完美再现出来
What a self-serving man, that king.
国王真是势利眼
He's the one who only gave us ten copper coins when we departed.
我们踏上旅途时 明明只给了我们十枚铜币
Now, now, Frieren.
好了 芙莉莲
Now we get to drink for free.
接下来就要免费畅饮了
Let's call it a deal.
这件事就先这样吧
Corrupt Priest.
酒肉僧侣
So it's over, huh?
结束了啊？
Yeah.
是啊
Our adventure ends here.
我们的冒险就到此结束了
Ten years, huh?
十年啊
So many things happened.
发生了不少事情呢
Like the day we departed…
我们出发的那天…
when Himmel and Eisen
辛美尔跟艾泽
spoke disrespectfully to the king and were almost executed.
因为说国王的坏话 差点就被处刑了
In the worst-case scenario, our adventure could have ended there.
最糟的状况就是 我们的冒险直接就在那里结束了
There was that time when Heiter was useless because of a hangover.
还曾有过海塔宿醉到 完全派不上用场的时候
You look like an undead, but are you okay?
你看起来就像活死人 没问题吗？
-I'm not. -You're not, huh?
-不行 -不行啊？
He was like that at least once a week.
他一周至少会有一次那种状况呢
Compared to that, I'm a model student.
相较之下 我算是很优秀了
When you were almost eaten by a mimic, we thought about leaving you behind.
你差点被宝箱怪吃掉的时候 我还想说放着你不管算了
How many times did we say that it was a trap? Seriously?
都说过几次有陷阱了 怎么还中招？
Can we leave this elf behind?
可以丢下这个精灵不管吗？
Jeez…
真是的…
We only have lousy memories.
真是有够惨的回忆啊
But it was fun.
但是很快乐
I'm glad I was able to go on an adventure with you all.
能跟你们一起冒险真是太好了
I agree.
说得没错
Although it was only a short while.
虽然时间很短就是了
Short? What are you talking about? It was ten years.
很短？你在说什么啊？有十年耶
Look at Heiter. He's become such an old man.
你看海塔 他已经变成大叔了
-That's rude. -He was always like that.
-没礼貌 -他本来就是那样啊
That's rude.
没礼貌
It's about time.
快开始了
The Era Meteor Shower, was it?
好像是叫做半世纪流星吧？
A meteor shower that happens once every 50 years.
五十年一次的流星雨
It's a perfect start to an era of peace.
作为和平时代的开始再适合不过了
How beautiful.
真漂亮
It's hard to see in the middle of the city.
在城镇里很难看清楚
We're getting emotional over here. Can you try to read the mood?
气氛正感动耶 不会看状况讲话吗？
Then, next time…
那么下次…
In 50 years, I'll show you to a place that I know with a better view.
五十年后 我带你们 去一个能看得更清楚的地方吧
-What? -No…
-干嘛？ -不…
It's nothing.
没什么
Okay, let's all go to see it.
说得对 大家一起去看吧
All right, I'm going this way.
好 那我要往这边走了
What are you going to do now?
你接下来要做什么？
I'll continue my pursuit of magic.
我要继续收集魔法
I plan to travel around the central lands for about 100 years.
花个一百年左右游遍中央诸国
So, I'll visit from time to time.
我偶尔会来拜访你们的
An elf's perception of time is unfathomable.
精灵的时间观真是难以理解啊
Seriously, how long has she been alive?
真是的 她到底活了多久啊？
I bet to her,
说不定对她而言
50 years and 100 years don't make much of a difference.
五十年或是一百年没有太大分别吧
A shadow dragon's horn?
暗黑龙的角？
We don't sell that here.
我们这里没卖那个
I haven't seen a shadow dragon around for two to three decades.
我至少二、三十年 没看过暗黑龙的角了
I see. What should I do…? I need it to summon…
这样啊 那怎么办？ 我需要用它来召唤…
That reminds me, I entrusted the one I found
说起来 在魔王城堡找到的那个
in the Demon King's castle to Himmel.
我交给辛美尔了
Um, it's exuding some kind of evil aura.
这一直散发出邪恶的气息耶
It's not harmful, is it?
对人体无害吧？
-I don't know. -You don't know?
-我不知道 -你不知道？
It's almost time for the Era Meteor Shower anyway.
反正看半世纪流星雨的时间也快到了
I guess I'll go get it.
就顺便去找他拿吧
The townscape is quite different from the last time I was here.
镇上的景色跟上次来的时候很不一样
It should be around here.
应该在这附近
Frieren?
芙莉莲？
Himmel…
辛美尔…
-You're a feeble old man… -Well, that's rude.
-你变成老头子了… -说得太过分了吧
I've grown old, but I'm still handsome, aren't I?
我就算上了年纪也还是个帅哥吧？
It's been 50 years.
已经过去五十年了
You look just like you did back then.
你的样子还是跟以前一样没变
I thought I would never see you again.
我还以为这辈子不会再见到你了
The Era Meteor Shower, huh?
半世纪流星吗？
That brings back memories.
真令人怀念
Also, about that thing I found in the Demon King's castle…
还有 在魔王城堡捡到的东西…
The shadow dragon's horn, right?
你是指暗黑龙的角吧？
Not a day went by without me thinking about it.
我没有哪天不记着那个东西
After all, there was constantly an evil aura coming out of the drawer.
毕竟它一直 从柜子里散发出邪恶的气息
Sorry about that…
总觉得有点抱歉…
You could've just tossed it into a shed or something.
其实你大可随便 丢进仓库之类的地方就好了
How could I do that?
那怎么可以？
You may have left it with me without much thought,
你也许没有多想就把东西交给我了
but to me,
但对我而言
it was something important that was entrusted to me by a special comrade.
这是重要的伙伴托付给我的贵重物品
It was something I needed to return to you one day, just like this.
总有一天要交还给你
It's really not that important.
明明不是什么重要的东西
Himmel, are you ready?
辛美尔 还没好吗？
You're bald, so there's no point in caring too much.
你都秃头了 精心打扮也没有意义啊
Bald people still have their preferences.
就是秃子也有秃子的纠结
All right, let's go see the Era Meteor Shower.
那么出发去看半世纪流星吧
You look so distinguished now, Heiter.
你看起来很气派呢 海塔
I'm a bishop in the Holy City now.
我现在是圣都的主教啊
You haven't changed at all.
你一点都没变呢
Stop patting my head.
不准摸我的头
Eisen, you haven't changed much.
艾泽 你也没什么变呢
-Yeah? You think so? -You're a dwarf after all.
-是吗？看起来是那样吗？ -真不愧是矮人
So, where is this place with a great view?
所以看得很清楚的好地方在哪？
We're going there now?
现在就要去了？
It's still a little early for the Era Meteor Shower.
距离看半世纪流星的时间还有点早吧
Yeah, so we'll walk for about a week from here.
没错 从这里出发要走上一星期左右
-It's that far? -Jeez…
-那么远吗？ -真是的…
What a way to abuse the elderly.
让老人走这么远
This brings back memories. When we're like this,
真怀念啊 这样子让我感觉
I feel as if I've gone back in time.
好像回到以前那个时候
We traveled to many places, didn't we?
回到那个旅行过很多地方的时候
Everything was so new
一切都很新鲜
and appeared to be sparkling.
而且看起来熠熠生辉
All of you were always a part of my beautiful memories.
而你们的身影都在我美丽的回忆中
You know,
我啊
I've always looked forward to the day when we could all get together again.
一直满心期盼大家重新聚首的那天
Thank you, Frieren.
谢谢你 芙莉莲
Thanks to you,
多亏了你
I was able to enjoy one last adventure.
我才能享受最后一趟冒险
How beautiful.
真漂亮
I'm sure Himmel was happy.
我相信辛美尔很幸福
You think so?
是吗？
That girl was Sir Himmel's comrade?
那孩子是辛美尔大人的同伴？
She doesn't even look sad.
她脸上一点悲伤都没有
How heartless!
真是无情！
My, my! We don't look sad either!
哎呀呀 我们脸上也没有悲伤呢！
-Bishop, take it more seriously! -How heartless!
-神父 正经点好不好！ -真是冷血！
They're so harsh.
还真是毫不留情呢
I mean,
因为我…
I don't know anything about him.
对这个人根本一点都不了解
We traveled together for merely ten years, that's all.
我们仅是一起旅行了十年 仅此而已
Humans have a short lifespan.
人类的寿命很短
I knew that.
这点我早就知道了
So why didn't I try
所以说我为什么
to get to know him better?
没有试着多了解他一点呢？
Stop patting my head.
不要摸我的头
All right, I'd better head back to the Holy City.
好了 那我也要回去圣都了
Let me get a good look at you two.
让我好好看看你们两个
I'm sure this will be the last time.
这次一别应该就是永别了
Are you ill?
你身体哪里不对吗？
My drinking habits have caught up with me.
经年累月喝太多酒了
It must be punishment.
一定是报应
If you ever visit the Holy City,
有机会来圣都的话
leave some alcohol by my grave.
就顺路带酒去探望我的墓地吧
Heiter, you're not afraid to die?
海塔 难道你不害怕死亡吗？
We're the party of heroes that saved this world.
我们可是拯救了世界的勇者一行
After I die, I'm promised a lavish life in heaven.
死了之后一定会上天堂享乐的
That's the reason why I fought alongside you all in the first place.
正因如此 我才会跟你们一起战斗喔
Corrupt Priest.
酒肉僧侣
Well then, I'll be off.
那么我先走了
All right, I'll get going too.
好了 我也要出发了
A trip to pursue magic?
是收集魔法的旅途吗？
Yeah, that too.
嗯 那个也在其中
But I also want to get to know humans better.
但我也想更加了解人类
I see.
这样啊
I have something to ask you. Since I'm a mage,
我有事想拜托你 因为我是魔法使
I could use a strong vanguard.
要是有前卫在就能帮上大忙了
Give me a break.
饶了我吧
I'm too old to be wielding an axe.
我已经老到没力气挥斧头了
Don't look at me like that, Frieren.
别那样看我 芙莉莲
Once you start aging, it's a surprisingly long journey from there.
一旦开始衰老之后 人生意外地还有很长的路要走呢
I see.
是吗？
-See you, Eisen. -See you.
-那再见了 艾泽 -再见
I just saw this tree. I always get lost in this forest.
我刚刚看过这棵树 在树林中我总是迷路呢
Where am I?
我在哪里？
20 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF THE HERO HIMMEL
（勇者辛美尔逝世的二十年后）
THE OUTSKIRTS OF THE HOLY CITY, STRAHL IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央诸国的圣都斯特拉尔郊外）
Are you looking for something?
您在找什么吗？
Is something wrong?
请问怎么了？
No, I was looking for the house of someone named Heiter.
没什么 我正在找 一个叫海塔的人的家
Then you must be a visitor.
那您就是客人了
You are still alive, Corrupt Priest?
你还活着啊 酒肉僧侣？
Turns out, it's not so easy to die in a dignified way.
看来想死得潇洒点也不是那么容易
I bought alcohol to leave at your grave.
我买了要供奉你墓地的酒
You want to drink?
要喝一杯吗？
-I've stopped drinking already. -I see.
-我已经戒酒了 -这样啊
I think it's too late to start behaving for the goddess to forgive you.
我想事到如今就是装成乖孩子 女神也不会原谅你了
Thank you.
谢谢你
-Who is that? -Her name is Fern.
-那孩子是谁？ -她叫做菲伦
She was a war orphan from the Southern lands.
是南方诸国战乱时的孤儿
How surprising.
一点都不像你呢
You're not the type to voluntarily help people.
你不是那种会主动帮助别人的人
That's Himmel's job.
又不是辛美尔
Frieren, why did you visit me?
芙莉莲 为什么你会来找我？
I'm on my way to the Holy City.
我正要前往圣都 就顺路来看看
I make it a point to keep in touch with whoever I meet on the road.
我会尽量联系在路上能见到的人
Plus, I owe a lot to you, Heiter.
而且我还欠你很多人情 海塔
I wanted to return the favor before you died.
我想在你死前还你人情
Then let me ask you for a favor.
那我有件事想拜托你
Will you take an apprentice?
你要不要收个徒弟？
Fern has the potential to become a mage.
菲伦具备能够成为魔法使的潜能
Will you take her along with you on your travels?
你能带她跟你一起去旅行吗？
Sorry, Heiter. I can't do that.
对不起 海塔 这个我办不到
She'll just be a burden.
她只会是累赘而已
You know the mortality rate of mage apprentices on the battlefield.
你也清楚 见习魔法使在战场上的死亡率吧
I'm not going to let a friend's child left in my care die like that.
我不会让朋友托付的孩子 就这样去送死
I see.
这样啊
Then I have another favor.
那就换件事吧
This was excavated from the grave of Ewig the Sage.
这是从贤者埃维希的墓地出土的东西
They say this grimoire contains long-lost spells regarding
据说这本魔导书记载了失传已久的
the resurrection of the dead and immortality.
复活魔法以及长生不死的魔法
I doubt such magic really exists.
我很怀疑那种魔法真的存在
That's why I want you to decipher it.
所以我才希望你能解读它
Can you do that?
可以吗？
It's encoded in pictures, right?
这是用了图画暗号吧？
People of this era sure loved this kind of stuff.
那个时代的人很喜欢这种东西
It'll only take five to six years.
大概花个五、六年就可以了
I see.
这样啊
What's the point in deciphering this anyway?
但是你解读这本书要做什么？
I thought you weren't afraid to die?
你不是不害怕死亡吗？
I have two reasons.
有两个理由
One, I was just trying to act cool in front of you two.
一是当年我只是在你们面前故作潇洒
Two, compared to then, I am more afraid of dying now.
二是跟当年相比 我现在更害怕死亡了
Well, even if I can't become immortal, I just wanted…
就算不能长生不死 我也希望…
I just wanted a little more time, that's all.
一点点就好 能再活久一点就好了
Besides, the scriptures tell us to live in good health.
而且圣典也说了 要我们健康地活着
Longevity is the prime example of that, Frieren.
长寿可谓是健康的典范喔 芙莉莲
Corrupt Priest.
酒肉僧侣
Also,
另外
if you have time in between your efforts to decipher that,
在解读之余的空档
will you be able to teach Fern magic?
你能不能教菲伦魔法呢？
I'm a priest, so I'm not very good with that.
我是主教 所以不太擅长魔法
Sure, I can do that.
当然 那样我没问题
There you are.
找到你了
I had trouble finding you. Do you always train in the forest?
要找到你真是不容易 你向来都在森林里修行吗？
Mistress Frieren, even you had trouble finding me?
连芙莉莲大人要找到我都很难吗？
Master Heiter always says that my presence is undetectable.
海塔大人总是说我没什么存在感
It is a very good thing.
这真是好事一件呢
Yeah.
是啊
Just as I thought…
如我所料…
I can barely detect her mana.
几乎探测不到她的魔力
That requires remarkable mana control.
在控制魔力上 要做到这点可是要费不少功夫呢
How hard did she study to be able to do that at her age?
才这个年纪 到底是付出多少精力去研究啊？
Master Heiter
海塔大人说过
said that he'll consider me fully qualified if I can pierce that rock.
如果能将那块石头射穿的话 我就是独当一面的魔法使了
Heiter knows what he's talking about. That is--
海塔很懂呢 那是…
As you can see, my mana disperses and doesn't reach it.
就像这样子 我的魔力会散开来 没办法抵达那里
I see.
原来如此
What kind of training do I need to do?
我应该进行怎样的修行才好呢？
Hey, can I ask you something first?
我能先问你一件事吗？
Do you like magic?
你喜欢魔法吗？
To a moderate degree.
还可以
That's just like me.
跟我一样呢
-Trying to act cool again, Heiter? -How is your training with Fern?
-海塔 你又想装潇洒了？ -菲伦的修行顺利吗？
-Magic is so amazing. -It's worth looking for.
-魔法真的好厉害 -值得去找找看
-It'd be a waste to die. -One day I want to show you.
-死了就太可惜了 -真希望有一天能让你看看
"It didn't have to be magic…"
也不一定要是魔法…
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵